part 2 chapter 5.
Sim had vanished.
A morning came, and he was missing from work: a few thoughtless people commented on his absence.
On the next day nobody mentioned him.
On the third day Winston went into the vestibule of the Records Department to
look at the notice board.
One of the notices carried a printed list of the members of the Chess
Committee, of whom Sim had been won It looked almost exactly as it had looked before—
—nothing had been crossed out— —but it was one name shorter.
It was enough Sim had ceased to exist: he had never existed.
The weather was baking hot.
In the labyrinthine Ministry the windowless, air-conditioned rooms kept to
their normal temperature, but outside the pavement scorched one's feet into the
stench of the Tubes that the rush hours was a horror.
The preparations for Hate Week were in full swing, and the staffs of all the
Ministries were working overtime.
Processions, meetings, military parades, lectures wax Works displays, film shows
tele-screen programs all had to be organized stands had to be erected, effigies built,
slogans coined, songs written rumors circulated, photographs faked.
Julia's unit in the Fiction Department had been taken off the production of
novels and was rushing out a series of atrocity pamphlets.
Winston, in addition to his regular work, spent long periods every day in going
through the back files of the Times and altering and embellishing news items
which were to be quoted in speeches.
Late at night, when crowds of rowdy polls roamed the streets, the town had a
curiously febrile heir The rocket bombs crashed oftener than ever, and sometimes
in the far distance there were enormous explosions which no one could explain
and about which there were wild rumors The new tune which was to be the theme
song of Hate Week (the Hate Song, it was called) had already been composed and was
being endlessly plugged on the telescreens.
It had a savage, barking rhythm which could not exactly be called music, but
resembled the beating of a drum rolled out by hundreds of voices to the
of marching feet, it was terrifying.
The pros had taken a fancy to it, and in the midnight streets it competed with
the still popular It was only a hopeless fancy'.
The Parsons children played it at all hours of the night and day, unbearably, on
a comb and a piece of toilet paper.
Winston's evenings were fuller than ever.
Squads of volunteers organized by Parsons, were preparing the street for
Hate Week, stitching banners, painting posters, erecting flagstaffs on the roofs
and perilously slinging wires across the street for the reception of streamers.
Parsons boasted the Victory Mansions alone would display 400 meters of
bunting. He was in his native element and as happy as a lark. The heat and the
manual work had even given him a pretext for reverting to shorts and an open
shirt in the evenings. He was everywhere at once, pushing, pulling, sawing, hammering,
improvising, jollying everyone along with comradly exhortations and giving out
from every fold of his body what seemed an inexhaustible supply of acrid smelling sweat foreign
ER had suddenly appeared all over London.
It had no caption, and represented simply the monstrous figure of Eurasian soldier,
three or four meters high, striding forward with expressionless Mongolian
face and enormous boots, a submachine gun pointed from his hip.
From whatever angle you looked at the poster, the muzzle of the gun, magnified
by the foreshortening, seemed to be pointed straight at you.
The thing had been plastered on every blank space on every wall, even
outnumbering the portraits of Big Brother.
The pros normally apathetic about the war, were being lashed into one of their
periodical frenzies of patriotism. As though to harmonize with the general
mood, the rocket bombs had been killing larger numbers of people than usual.
One fell on a crowded film theater in Stepney, burying several hundred victims among the ruins.
The whole population of the neighborhood turned out for a long, trailing funeral
which went on for hours and was in effect an indignation meeting.
Another bomb fell on a piece of waste ground which was used as a playground,
and several dozen children were blown to pieces.
There were further angry demonstrations, Goldstein was burned in effigy, hundreds
of copies of the poster of the Eurasian soldier were torn down and added to the
flames, and a number of shops were looted in the turmoil;
then a rumor flew around that spies were directing the rocket bombs by means of
wireless waves, and an old couple who were suspected of being a foreign
extraction had their house set on fire and perished of suffocation.
In the room over Mr cherrington's shop, when they could get there, Julia and
Winston lay side by side on a stripped bed under the open Windows naked for the
sake of coolness.
The rat had never come back, but the bugs had multiplied hideously in the heat.
It did not seem to matter.
Dirty or clean, the room was paradise.
As soon as they arrived they would sprinkle everything with pepper bought
on the black market, tear off their clothes and make love with sweating
bodies, then fall asleep and wake to find that the bugs had rallied and were
massing for the counter-attack Four, five, six— —seven times they met during the month of June.
Winston had dropped his habit of drinking gin at all hours. He seemed to
have lost the need for it.
He had grown fatter, his varicus also had subsided, leaving only a brown stain on
the skin above his ankle, his fits of coughing in the early morning had stopped.
The process of life had ceased to be intolerable, he had no longer any impulse
to make faces at the tele screen or shout curses at the top of his voice.
Now that they had a secure Hiding Place almost a home, it did not even seem a
hardship that they could only meet him frequently and for a couple of hours at a time.
What mattered was that the room over the junk shop should exist.
To know that it was there in Violet was almost the same as being in it.
The room was a world, a pocket of the past where extinct animals could walk
to Charrington, thought Winston, was another extinct animal.
He usually stops to talk with Mr Charrington for a few minutes on his way upstairs.
The old man seemed seldom or never to go out of doors, and on the other hand to
have almost no customers.
He led a ghost-like existence between the tiny, dark shop and an even tinier
back kitchen where he prepared his meals and which contained, among other things,
an unbelievably ancient gramophone with an enormous horn.
He seemed glad of the opportunity to talk wondering about among his worthless
stock, with his long nose and thick spectacles and his bowed shoulders in
the velvet jacket, he had always vaguely the heir of being a collector rather than a tradesman.
With a sort of faded enthusiasm he would finger this scrap of rubbish or that— —a
china bottle stopper the painted lid of a broken snuff box a pinch back locket
containing a strand of some long dead baby's hair— —never asking that Winston should buy it,
merely that he should admire it.
To talk to him was like listening to the tinkling of a worn out musical box
He had dragged out from the corners of his memory some more fragments of forgotten rhymes.
There was one about Four and Twenty blackbirds, and another about a cow with
a crumpled horn, and another about the death of poor Robin.
'It just occurred to me you might be interested,' he would say with a
deprecating little laugh whenever he produced a new fragment.
But he could never recall more than a few lines of any one rhyme.
Both of them knew— —in a way, it was never out of their minds— —that what was now
happening could not last long.
There were times when the fact of impending death seemed as palpable as
the bed they lay on, and they would cling together with a sort of despairing
sensuality, like a damned soul grasping at his last morsel of pleasure when the
clock is within five minutes of striking.
But there were also times when they had the illusion not only of safety but of permanence.
So long as they were actually in this room, they both felt, no harm could come to them.
Getting there was difficult and dangerous, but the room itself was sanctuary.
It was as when Winston had gazed into the heart of the paperweight, with the
feeling that it would be possible to get inside that classy world, and that once
inside it time could be arrested.
Often they gave themselves up to daydreams of escape.
Their luck would hold indefinitely, and they would carry on their intrigue, just
like this, for the remainder of their natural lives.
Or Catherine would die, and by subtle maneuverings Winston and Julia would
succeed in getting married.
Or they would commit suicide together.
Or they would disappear, alter themselves out of recognition, learn to speak with
proletarian accents, get jobs in a factory and live out their lives undetected in a Backstreet
It was all nonsense, as they both knew. In reality there was no escape. Even the one
plan that was practicable, suicide, they had no intention of carrying out.
To hang on from day to day and from week to week, spinning out a present that had
no future, seemed an uncomfortable instinct, just as one's lungs will always
draw the next breath so long as there is air available.
Sometimes, too, they talked of engaging in active rebellion against the Party, but
with no notion of how to take the first step.
Even if the fabulous Brotherhood was a reality, there still remained the
difficulty of finding one's way into it.
He told her of the strange intimacy that existed, or seemed to exist, between
himself and O'Brien, and of the impulse he sometimes felt, simply to walk into
O'Brien's presence announced that he was the enemy of the Party and demand his help.
Curiously enough this did not strike her as an impossibly rash thing to do.
She was used to judging people by their faces, and it seemed natural to her that
Winston should believe O'Brien to be trustworthy on the strength of a single flash of the eyes.
Moreover she took it for granted that everyone, or nearly everyone, secretly
hated the Party and would break the rules if he thought it's safe to do so.
But she refused to believe that widespread organized opposition existed
or could exist. The tales about Goldstein and his underground army, she said, were
simply a lot of rubbish which the Party had invented for its own purposes and
which you had to pretend to believe in.
Times beyond number, at Party rallies and spontaneous demonstrations, she had
shouted at the top of her voice for the execution of people whose name she had
never heard and in whose supposed crime she had not the faintest belief.
When public trials were happening she had taken her place in the detachments
from the Youth League who surrounded the courts from morning to night, chanting at
intervals 'Death to the traitors!'
During the Two Minutes Hate she always excelled all others in shouting insults
at Goldstein and she had only the dimmest idea of who Goldstein was and
what doctrines he was supposed to represent.
She had grown up since the Revolution and was too young to remember the
ideological battles of the 50s and 60s Such a thing as an independent political
movement was outside her imagination: and in any case the Party was invincible.
It would always exist, and it would always be the same.
You could only rebel against it by secret disobedience or, at most, by
isolated acts of violence such as killing somebody or blowing something up.
In some ways she was far more acute than Winston, and far less susceptible to Party propaganda.
Once when he happened in some connection to mention the war against Eurasia, she
startled him by saying casually that in her opinion the war was not happening.
The rocket bombs which fell daily on London were probably fired by the
Government of Oceania itself, 'just to keep people frightened'.
This was an idea that had literally never occurred to him. She also stirred a
sort of envy in him by telling him that during the Two Minutes Hate her greater
difficulty was to avoid bursting out laughing.
But she only questioned the teachings of the Party when they in some way touched
upon her own life. Often she was ready to accept the official mythology, simply
because the difference between truth and falsehood did not seem important to her.
She believed, for instance, having learned it at school, that the Party had invented airplanes
In his own school days Winston remembered, in the late 50s it was only
the helicopter that the Party claimed to have invented; a dozen years later, when Julia was at
school, it was already claiming the airplane one generation mourned it would
be claiming the steam engine.)
And when he told her that airplanes had been in existence before he was born, and
long before the Revolution, the fact struck her as totally uninteresting.
After all, what did it matter who had invented airplanes It was rather more of
a shock to him when he discovered from some chance remark that she did not
remember that Oceania, four years ago, had been at war with East Asia and at peace with Eurasia.
It was true that she regarded the whole war as a sham: but apparently she had not
even noticed that the name of the enemy had changed.
'I thought we'd always been at war with Eurasia,' she said vaguely.
It frightened him a little. The invention of airplanes dated from long before her
birth, but the switchover in the war had happened only four years ago, well after
she was grown up.
He argued with her about it for perhaps a quarter of an hour.
In the end he succeeded in forcing her memory back until she did dimly recall
that at one time East Asia and not Eurasia had been the enemy.
But the issue still struck her as unimportant.
'Who cares?' she said impatiently. 'It's always one bloody war after another,
and one knows the news is all lies anyway.'
Sometimes he talked to her of the Records Department and the impudent
forgeries that he committed there.
Such things did not appear to horrify her.
She did not feel the abyss opening beneath her feet at the thought of lies becoming truths.
He told her the story of Jones, Aaronson and Rutherford and the momentous slip of
paper which he had once held between his fingers.
It did not make much impression on her.
At first, indeed, she failed to grasp the point of the story.
'Were they friends of yours?' she said.
'No, I never knew them. They were Inner Party members. Besides, they were far
older men than I was. They belonged to the old days, before the Revolution.
I barely knew them by sight and what was there to worry about? People
are being killed off all the time, aren't they?'
He tried to make her understand.
'This was an exceptional case.
It wasn't just a question of somebody being killed. Do you realize that the
past, starting from yesterday, has been actually abolished?
If it survives anywhere, it's in a few solid objects with no words attached to
them, like that lump of glass there.
Already we know almost literally nothing about the Revolution in the years before
the Revolution.
Every record has been destroyed or falsified, every book has been Rewritten
every picture has been repainted every statue and street and building has been
renamed every date has been altered.
And that process is continuing day by day and minute by minute. History has
stopped. Nothing exists except an endless present in which the Party is always right.
I know, of course, that the past is falsified, but it would never be possible
for me to prove it, even when I did the falsification myself.
After the thing is done, no evidence ever remains. The only evidence is inside my
own mind, and I don't know with any certainty that any other human being shares my memories.
Just in that one instance, in my whole life, I did possess actual concrete
evidence after the event— —years after it.'
'And what good was that?'
'It was no good, because I threw it away a few minutes later. But if the same thing
happened today, I should keep it.'
'Well, I wouldn't!' said Julia. 'I'm quite ready to take risks, but only for
something worthwhile not for bits of old newspaper.
What could you have done with it even if you had kept it?'
'Not much, perhaps. But it was evidence.
It might have planted a few doubts here and there, supposing that I'd dared to
show it to anybody.
I don't imagine that we can alter anything in our own lifetime. But one can
imagine little knots of resistance spinning up here and there— —small groups
of people banding themselves together, and gradually growing, and even leaving a
few records behind, so that the next Generations can carry on where we leave off.'
'I'm not interested in the next generation, dear. I'm interested in us.'
'You're only a rebel from the waist downwards,' he told her.
She thought this brilliantly witty and flung her arms around him in the light
In the ramifications of Party doctrine she had not the faintest interest.
Whenever he began to talk of the principles of ensoc doublethink, the
mutability of the past and the denial of objective reality, and to use Newspeak
words, she became bored and confused and said that she never paid any attention
to that kind of thing.
One knew that it was all rubbish, so why let oneself be worried by it?
She knew when to cheer and went to boo, and that was all one needed.
If he persisted in talking of such subjects, she had a disconcerting habit of falling asleep.
She was one of those people who can go to sleep at any hour and in any position.
Talking to her, he realized how easy it was to present an appearance of
orthodoxy while having no grasp whatever of what orthodoxy meant. In a way, the
world view of the Party imposed itself most successfully on people incapable of
understanding it.
They could be made to accept the most flagrant violations of reality, because
they never fully grasped the enormity of what was demanded of them, and were not
sufficiently interested in public events to notice what was happening.
By lack of understanding they remains sane.
They simply swallowed everything, and what they swallowed did them no harm,
because it left no residue behind, just as a grain of corn will pass undigested
through the body of a bird